Guide to the Joseph Clancy Papers
Special Collections, University of Washington Libraries
Joseph Clancy papers
1921-1972
1940-1960
University of Washington Libraries Special Collections Box 352900 Seattle, WA 98195-2900
2218
2218-001
Clancy, Joseph,$d -1973
1.96 cubic feet (4 boxes)
Joseph Clancy was Secretary of the International Brotherhood of Boilermakers, Iron Ship Builders and Helpers of America, Local 104, in Seattle, Washington from 1941 to 1972. This collection spans the years 1921-1972 and contains constitutions and bylaws, correspondence, minutes, legal materials, news clippings, publications, ephemera, photographs, and a scrapbook created and/or kept by Clancy during his time as officer of Local 104.
Joseph Clancy was Secretary of the International Brotherhood of Boilermakers, Iron Ship Builders and Helpers of America, Local 104, in Seattle, Washington from 1941 to 1972. In 1946, tensions escalated between International President Charles J. MacGowan and members of Local 104 after the president attempted to take control of the Local through an appointed board of governors. Clancy and fellow officer Bill Miller were subsequently tried and suspended from the local after refusing to turn over Local 104's funds, newspaper, and records to MacGowan. Initially MacGowan's actions were upheld after the case was first taken to the Seattle superior court by members of the local; however, this decision was reversed several years later by the Washington State Supreme Court. The local was given back control over elections of officers, and Clancy was re-elected to Local 104 in the mid-1950s. Clancy passed away in 1973 shortly after finishing his term as union Secretary in 1972.
The collection is arranged into the following series:
SERIES I: CONSTITUTIONS AND BYLAWS
SERIES II: CORRESPONDENCE
SERIES III: MEETING MINUTES
SERIES IV: OFFICE FILES
SERIES V: LEGAL MATERIALS
SERIES VI: PRINTED MATERIALS AND EPHEMERA
SERIES VII: PHOTOGRAPHS
The Joseph Clancy papers span the years 1921-1972 and contain records related to Clancy's work as Secretary of the International Brotherhood of Boilermakers, Iron Ship Builders and Helpers of America, Local 104 in Seattle, Washington. A majority of the materials pertain to International President MacGowan's efforts to take control of Local 104 and the trial and suspension of Clancy and Bill Miller from the union. Also included are records related to the activities of Local 72 in Portland, Oregon.
The collection also contains a scrapbook, likely compiled by Clancy, containing news clippings, photographs, correspondence, election materials, printed materials, and ephemera related to the IBB. Loose materials previously folded into the scrapbook were removed for preservation reasons, placed in folders, and housed with the other foldered materials. This is denoted in the folder titles for these materials.
The following is a detailed description of materials within each series:
SERIES I: CONSTITUTIONS AND BYLAWS contains IBB International, Local 104, and Local 72 constitutions and bylaws.
SERIES II: CORRESPONDENCE contains official notices sent to members of Local 104 from International President Charles J. MacGowan; letters from MacGowan to Clancy regarding Clancy’s hearing and suspension as Secretary of Local 104; and outgoing correspondence from Clancy regarding workers' injuries and deaths, dues, and other local matters.
SERIES III: MEETING MINUTES contains minutes of Local 104, the Everett Central Labor Council, Labor’s General Caucus, and the Pacific Coast Zone Ship Repair Conference meetings.
SERIES IV: OFFICE FILES contains financial records, reports, officer and member lists, and notes related to activities of Local 104.
SERIES V: LEGAL MATERIALS contains resolutions, agreements, and court proceedings between the International and Locals 104 and 72 as well as Joseph Clancy's hearing report.
SERIES VI: PRINTED MATERIALS AND EPHEMERA contains convention proceedings and publications; Local 104 election materials; state election and legislative initiatives materials, including Right to Work Initiative 202; political cartoons and flyers; news clippings; labor publications and newspapers; and Clancy's organizational membership and special event memorabilia.
SERIES VII: PHOTOGRAPHS contains black and white prints of various sizes, including images of Clancy with other Local 104 officers as well as official group photographs and candid images taken at labor conventions.
Open to all users.
Donated by Patrick Clancy, 1/9/1974
Clancy, Joseph,$d -1973$vArchives; Edwards, Herbert M.; Edmundson, W. D.; Mitchell, Hugh B.$q(Hugh Burnton),$d1907-1996; Labor Archives of Washington (University of Washington); International Brotherhood of Boilermakers, Iron Ship Builders, and Helpers of America.$bLocal 104 (Seattle, Wash.); International Brotherhood of Boilermakers, Iron Ship Builders, and Helpers of America
Personal Papers/Corporate Records; Labor History; Labor Unions; Washington (State); Seattle
- CONSTITUTIONS AND BYLAWS, 1940-1972; SERIES I (Box-folder 1/1-1/3)
  - International Brotherhood of Boilermakers Local 72 (Portland, OR) Proposed Bylaws, c. 1940-1960 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - International Brotherhood of Boilermakers Local 104 Bylaws, 1943-1972 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - International Brotherhood of Boilermakers International Constitutions, 1953-1969 (Box-folder 1/3)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1940-1960; SERIES II (Box-folder 1/4-1/10)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1944-1946 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1947-1949 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1950-1958 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Incoming Correspondence, c. 1940-1960 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Outgoing Letters, 1942-1956 (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Outgoing Letters, c. 1940-1949 (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Scrapbook Loose Materials: Correspondence, 1944-1960 (Box-folder 1/10)
- MEETING MINUTES, 1943-1954; SERIES III (Box-folder 1/11-1/16)
  - Meeting Minutes: Local 104, 1946-1950 (Box-folder 1/11)
  - Meeting Minutes: Everett Central Labor Council, 1954 April 21 (Box-folder 1/12)
  - Meeting Minutes: Labor's General Caucus, 1944 April 29 (Box-folder 1/13)
  - Meeting Minutes: Pacific Coast Zone Ship Repair Conference, 1947 May (Box-folder 1/14)
  - Meeting Minutes: Local 104 [?], 1947-1949 (Box-folder 1/15)
  - Meeting Minutes: Pacific Coast Shipbuilding Zone Conference, 1943 July (Box-folder 1/16)
- OFFICE FILES, 1941-1956; SERIES IV (Box-folder 2/1-2/8)
  - Financial Records, 1941-1949 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - International Brotherhood of Boilermakers, Iron Ship Builders and Helpers News Updates from International President MacGowan, 1947-1948 (Box-folder 2/2)
  - Washington State Federation of Labor General Election Endorsements, 1948 October 2 (Box-folder 2/3)
  - Business Agent's Reports to Local 104, 1948-1956 (Box-folder 2/4)
  - Local 104 Audit Reports, 1946-1947 (Box-folder 2/5)
  - Officer and Member Lists, c. 1940-1950 (Box-folder 2/6)
  - Local 104 Assorted Materials, c.1945-1947 (Box-folder 2/7)
  - Handwritten Notes, 1942-1953 (Box-folder 2/8)
- LEGAL MATERIALS, 1937-1955; SERIES V (Box-folder 2/9-2/12)
  - Resolutions, c. 1940-1949 (Box-folder 2/9)
  - Master Agreements: Boilermakers, Metal Trades, and Shipbuilders, 1937-1955 (Box-folder 2/10)
  - Working Agreement Between Boilermakers Local 104 and Office Employees' International Union Local 8, 1946 March 01 (Box-folder 2/11)
  - Court Papers, c. 1942-1947 (Box-folder 2/12)
    - Joseph Clancy's Hearing Report, 1946 December 05
- PRINTED MATERIALS AND EPHEMERA, 1921-1969; SERIES VI (Box-folder 2/13-2/14, 3/1-3/16, 4/1, Map Case Drawer E2)
  - Education- Labor Day event packet: Teaching in Seattle Public Schools, 1952 (Box-folder 2/13)
  - International Brotherhood of Boilermakers, Iron Ship Builders and Helpers 19th Consolidated Convention Proceedings, 1953 June 29-1953 July 07 (Box-folder 2/14)
  - International Brotherhood of Boilermakers, Iron Ship Builders and Helpers Convention Proceedings, 1941, 1947 (Box-folder 3/1)
  - Convention Publications, 1952, 1961 (Box-folder 3/2)
  - Speeches and Writings: Herb M. Edwards on Issues Within Union Leadership, Undated (Box-folder 3/3)
  - National Labor Relations Act Amendment, c. 1947 (Box-folder 3/4)
  - Labor Publications, 1945-1955 (Box-folder 3/5)
  - Local 104 Election Campaign Materials, c. 1946-1968 (Box-folder 3/6)
  - Public Elections Campaign and Legislative Initiatives Material, 1956-1958 (Box-folder 3/7)
  - News Clippings, c. 1940-1960 (Box-folder 3/8)
  - News Clippings, c.1940-1950 (Box-folder 3/9)
  - News Clippings, c. 1940-1969 (Box-folder 3/10)
  - Boiler Maker Business Agents, c. 1943-1950 (Box-folder 3/11)
  - Joseph Clancy's Organization Membership and Event Memorabilia, c. 1921-1959 (Box-folder 3/12)
  - Political Cartoons and Flyers, c. 1950-1956 (Box-folder 3/13)
  - Assorted Print Materials, c. 1943-1956 (Box-folder 3/14)
  - Scrapbook Loose Materials: Clancy vs. MacGowan Case, 1946-1949 (Box-folder 3/15)
  - Scrapbook Loose Materials: "The Freedom Pledge" poster, c. 1948 (Box-folder 3/16)
  - Scrapbook, c. 1940-1960 (Box-folder 4/1)
  - Union Newspapers, 1941, 1950, 1969 (Folder:oversize Oversize folder)
  - Scrapbook Loose Materials: Newspapers, 1942, 1946-1947 (Folder:oversize Oversize folder)
  - Local 72 and 104 Election Ballots, 1935-1956 (Folder:oversize Oversize folder)
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1947-1961; SERIES VII (Box-folder 3/17-3/19, Map Case Drawer E2)
  - Washington State Federation of Labor 14th Annual Convention in Bellingham: Photographs, 1941 July (Box-folder 3/17)
  - Local 104 Officers Clancy, Grosso, Johns, and Miller: Photographs, c. 1947 (Box-folder 3/18)
  - Convention Photographs, c. 1937-1961 (Box-folder 3/19)
  - Convention Photographs, c. 1944 (Folder:oversize Oversize folder)
    - International Brotherhood of Boilermakers, Iron Ship Builders and Helpers Convention: Opening Session Attendees in the Kansas City Municipal Auditorium, 1944 (Oversize folder)